<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <docs>https://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
    <title >Pages on Clemens Cords&#39; Homepage</title>
    <link>http://clemens-cords.com/page/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Clemens Cords&#39; Homepage</description>
    <image>
      <title>Pages on Clemens Cords&#39; Homepage</title>
      <link>http://clemens-cords.com/page/</link>
      <url>http://clemens-cords.com/rat_icon.png</url>
    </image>
    <ttl>1440</ttl>
    <generator>After Dark 9.2.3 (Hugo 0.68.3)</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 19:49:27 UT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://clemens-cords.com/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://clemens-cords.com/about/</link>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Cords</dc:creator>
      <guid>http://clemens-cords.com/about/</guid>
      <description>About This page describes me, my work and any information valuable to potential employers / partners. You can navigate to the appropriate section by clicking the links in the table of contents below.
A shorter, 1-page CV well suited for job applications can be found here
 Table of Contents  General Information
1.1 Nationality, Location
1.2 Natural Languages
 Curriculum Vitae
 Fields of Expertise
3.1 Statistics
3.2 Mathematics</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[About This page describes me, my work and any information valuable to potential employers / partners. You can navigate to the appropriate section by clicking the links in the table of contents below.
A shorter, 1-page CV well suited for job applications can be found here
 Table of Contents  General Information
1.1 Nationality, Location
1.2 Natural Languages
 Curriculum Vitae
 Fields of Expertise
3.1 Statistics
3.2 Mathematics
3.3 Bioinformatics
3.4 Computer Science
 Programming Languages
4.1 C&#43;&#43;
4.2 R
4.3 GLSL
4.4 Lua
4.5 Python
4.5 Other
 How to Contact Me
   General Information  Nationality: German, born in Berlin Location: Berlin, Germany Natural Languages:  German, fluent at academic level English, fluent at academic level    Curriculum Vitae  2013: Graduated from Lilienthal High school Berlin 2013 - 2014: Studied Math at TU Berlin 2015 - 2019: Studied Bioinformatics at FU Berlin 2017 - 2018: Statistics Tutoring and TA at Charité / FU Berlin 2019: Internship at seqan3, writing automated tests, performance optimization 2020: Graduated with a Bachelor of Bioinformatics 2020 - Present: Lockdown-Induced Independent Study of Mathematical Morphology, Image Processing, Deep Learning 2020 - 2021: Wrote crisp, a well-documented image processing library implementing spatial filters, spectral techniques, neural networks, etc. from scratch to show mastery of above-mentioned topics 2021 - Present: Wrote jluna, a jluna-C&#43;&#43; wrapper with focus on modernity and elegant access to meta features   Fields of Expertise Statistics  Statistical Classification Clinical Study Design &amp;amp; Evaluation Data Visualization Automated Analytical Report Generation  Mathematics  Algorithm Design Mathematical Morphology &amp;amp; Topology Numerical Optimization Deep Learning Visual Computing related Linear Algebra  Computer Science  Supervised Learning and Narrow AI Computer Vision Parallel Programming &amp;amp; Distributed Systems Performance Optimization Real-Time Rendering High-Throughput Text Indexing / Processing Automated Testing/Performance Evaluation User Interface/Experience Design Documentation  Bioinformatics  Genomic Text Alignment and Processing High-Throughput Image Analysis Medical Imaging   Programming Languages 5/5 [▮▮▮▮▮]  C&#43;&#43; 4 years of experience, including full-time usage in self-employment. Full mastery of all language features including meta-template programming, and C&#43;&#43;20 Ranges/Concepts.
High standard of style and documentation, strong background in automated testing and performance evaluation. Intimately familiar with performance optimization, parallelization, compile-time execution.
Strong familiarity with the standard library, boost, Eigen, SFML, seqan3, sol3, OpenGL, Google Test, Google Benchmark, Abseil and others.
4/5 [▮▮▮▮▯]  Julia While somewhat new to my toolbag, julia has become my go-to language if meta, LISP-like functionality is needed. I wrote [jluna](https://github.com/Clemapfel/crisp), a fully C&#43;&#43;  Julia wrapper not only to demonstrate my mastery of C&#43;&#43; but my familiarity of julia and my desire to make it slot into any of my future C&#43;&#43; projects effortlessly. For `jluna` I had to revese engineer many of the undocumented features of the julia C-API which gave me deeper insight into julias inner workings. 4/5 [▮▮▮▮▯]  GLSL Strong background in real-time rendering for scientific or artistic purposes, used extensively for gpu-side computation and hardware acceleration in [crisp](https://github.com/Clemapfel/crisp). Familiarity with OpenGL 1.0 to 3.2 and 3.3 or newer. 4/5 [▮▮▮▮▯]  Lua Extensive knowledge of all major language features including co-routines, debug library and c-interfaces. Extensively used in [crisp](https://github.com/Clemapfel/crisp) for code generation and file interface. 4/5 [▮▮▮▮▯]  R Data Science and Visualization language of choice. Strong background in statistical classification, data pipelines and medical data analysis. Taught R as a tutor at university. Highly familiar with ggplot, tidyr, dplyr and tidyverse in general.
3/5 [▮▮▮▯▯]  Python  Strong foundation in use for data- and text processing, back-end and data-bank interfacing usage. Taught python syntax and general usage as TA at university.  Other Languages While usually not directly applicable to my current position, I also have enough experience in the following languages to consider myself able to work with them in a professional context
  Language Proficiency   Swift 3/5 [▮▮▮▯▯]   Java
JS 2/5 [▮▮▯▯▯]    Matlab/Octave
Go
Ruby
Perl
Haskell
 1/5 [▮▯▯▯▯]   Latex 3/5 [▮▮▮▯▯]   HTML/CSS 2/5 [▮▮▯▯▯]    If you came across this page through my application or by finding it randomly, thank you for reading! Feel free to reach out to me via mail@clemens-cords.com or any of the outlets listed on the contact page.
C. Cords
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://clemens-cords.com/contact/</link>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Cords</dc:creator>
      <guid>http://clemens-cords.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>Professional Mail: mail@clemens-cords.com Phone: &#43;49 30 239 348 71 Github: https://github.com/Clemapfel Gitter: @Clemapfel Personal Discord: Clem#3196 Twitter: @not_birb </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[Professional Mail: mail@clemens-cords.com Phone: &#43;49 30 239 348 71 Github: https://github.com/Clemapfel Gitter: @Clemapfel Personal Discord: Clem#3196 Twitter: @not_birb ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pink Mint Wave</title>
      <link>http://clemens-cords.com/pink_mint_wave/</link>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Cords</dc:creator>
      <guid>http://clemens-cords.com/pink_mint_wave/</guid>
      <description></description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Swingy Lines</title>
      <link>http://clemens-cords.com/swingy_lines/</link>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Cords</dc:creator>
      <guid>http://clemens-cords.com/swingy_lines/</guid>
      <description></description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The String</title>
      <link>http://clemens-cords.com/neuron_string/</link>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Cords</dc:creator>
      <guid>http://clemens-cords.com/neuron_string/</guid>
      <description></description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
